{
    "id": "Ciencia_540",
    "claim": "A letter written by one of the most important minds in history was sold for $2.9 million at an auction this December 4th. Albert Einstein's 1954 Letter to Religious Philosopher Erik Gutkind is commonly known as God's Letter and presents a courteous Einstein but thoroughly questioning the concept of religion and of God in general. Christie's auction house expected to be sold at $1.5 million. It exceeded expectations. Considered one of the final statements in the religion versus science debate, said Peter Klarnet, lead book and manuscript specialist at Christie's auction house, in a statement he provided to CNN. The letter, written in German one year before Einstein's death and transcribed in English by Christie's, is a reaction to the 1952 Gutkind book, Choose Life: The Biblical Call of Revolt. While Einstein makes it clear that he and the philosopher have much in common with regard to the objective attitude of human life and community, he clearly and abundantly leaves his position on religion. The word God is nothing more than for me the expression and product of human weakness, the Bible is a collection of honorable legends, but still purely primitive, which however are quite childish, writes Einstein. Einstein was a German-born Jew who lost his religious faith at an early age and sometimes referred to himself as an agnostic. The letter reinforces his love and shared identity with the Jewish people, but it also calls Judaism, like all other religions  an incarnation of the most childish superstition. The letter, which was sold on eBay in 2012, was exhibited at the Pace Gallery in San Francisco in late November until its auction in New York. It is not Einstein's only missive that has attracted great interest in Christie's. In 2002, the auction house exhibited a 1939 written letter from Einstein to the then President of the United States, Franklin Delano Roosevelt. The letter warned Roosevelt of the dangers of nuclear bomb technology. Sold for over $2 million. I'm sorry.",
    "source": "cnnespanol.cnn.com",
    "date": "04/12/2018",
    "veracity": 1,
    "claims": [
        {
            "claim": "A letter written by one of the most important minds in history was sold for $2.9 million at an auction this December 4th.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "How much did a letter written by one of the most important minds in history sell for at auction?",
                    "answer": "$2.9 million"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "Who wrote the letter that sold for $9 million?",
                    "score": 0.7079,
                    "answers": "of the most important minds in history|prep"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What was the value of the letter written by one of the most important minds in history?",
                    "score": 0.6893,
                    "answers": "cnnespanol.cnn.com reported on 04/12/2018 that A letter written by one of the most important minds in history was sold for $ 2.9 million at an auction this December 4th|ROOT\tthat A letter written by one of the most important minds in history was sold for $ 2.9 million at an auction this December 4th|ccomp\tfor $ 2.9 million|prep\t$|quantmod\t2.9|compound"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is cnnespanol.cnn.com?",
                    "score": 0.5456,
                    "answers": "A|det\thistory|pobj"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "A letter written by one of the most important minds in history is commonly known as God's Letter and presents one of the most important minds in history but thoroughly questioning the concept of religion and of God in general.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "What is a letter written by one of the most important minds in history commonly known as?",
                    "answer": "God's Letter"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "Who wrote the letter \"God's Letter\"?",
                    "score": 0.801,
                    "answers": "A letter written by one of the most important minds in history|nsubjpass\twritten by one of the most important minds in history|acl\tby one of the most important minds in history|agent\tone of the most important minds in history|pobj\tin history|prep\t's|case\tin history|prep"
                },
                {
                    "question": "Who wrote God's Letter?",
                    "score": 0.7985,
                    "answers": "of the most important minds in history|prep\tthe most important minds in history|pobj\tof the most important minds in history|prep\tthe most important minds in history|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is God's Letter?",
                    "score": 0.7142,
                    "answers": "cnnespanol.cnn.com reported on 04/12/2018 that A letter written by one of the most important minds in history is commonly known as God 's Letter and presents one of the most important minds in history but thoroughly questioning the concept of religion and of God in general|ROOT\tA|det\tas God 's Letter|prep\tGod 's|poss\tGod 's Letter|pobj\tGod in general|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the letter written by one of the most important minds in history?",
                    "score": 0.7087,
                    "answers": "that|mark\tthe|det\tis|auxpass\tcommonly|advmod\tthe|det\tbut|cc\tthe|det"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the meaning of God's Letter?",
                    "score": 0.7,
                    "answers": "on 04/12/2018|prep\treligion|pobj\tof God in general|conj\tin general|prep\tgeneral|amod"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "Christie's auction house expected to be sold at $1.5 million.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "Who reported that Christie's auction house was expected to be sold at $1.5 million?",
                    "answer": "cnnespanol.cnn.com"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What is Christie's auction house expected to sell for?",
                    "score": 0.8619,
                    "answers": "cnnespanol.cnn.com|nsubj\tcnnespanol.cnn.com reported on 04/12/2018 that Christie 's auction house expected to be sold at $ 1.5 million|ROOT\tauction|compound\tthat Christie 's auction house expected to be sold at $ 1.5 million|ccomp\tto be sold at $ 1.5 million|xcomp"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "sold exceeded expectations.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "What website reported on 04/12/2018 that the sale of cnnespanol.cnn.cnn exceeded expectations?",
                    "answer": "cnnespanol.cnn.com"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "How many sales exceeded expectations?",
                    "score": 0.8868,
                    "answers": "that sold exceeded expectations|ccomp"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What did cnnespanol.cnn.com say about the sales exceeding expectations?",
                    "score": 0.8846,
                    "answers": "cnnespanol.cnn.com reported on 04/12/2018 that sold exceeded expectations|ROOT"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is cnnespanol.cnn.com?",
                    "score": 0.7076,
                    "answers": "cnnespanol.cnn.com|nsubj\ton 04/12/2018|prep\tthat|mark\tsold|nsubj\texpectations|dobj"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "Considered one of the final statements in the religion versus science debate, said Peter Klarnet, lead book and manuscript specialist at Christie's auction house , in a statement Peter Klarnet, lead book and manuscript specialist at Christie's auction house provided to CNN.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "What auction house did Peter Klarnet work for?",
                    "answer": "Christie's auction house"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What are the final statements in the religion versus science debate?",
                    "score": 0.7051,
                    "answers": "the final statements in the religion versus science debate|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is Peter Klarnet's position on religion versus science?",
                    "score": 0.6333,
                    "answers": "on 04/12/2018|prep\treligion versus science|nmod\tversus science|prep\tChristie 's|poss\t's|case\tChristie 's|poss\t's|case"
                },
                {
                    "question": "Who is Peter Klarnet?",
                    "score": 0.587,
                    "answers": "Peter|compound\tPeter Klarnet , lead book and manuscript specialist at Christie 's auction house|nsubj\tlead|amod\tbook and manuscript|nmod\tlead book and manuscript specialist at Christie 's auction house|appos\tin a statement Peter Klarnet , lead book and manuscript specialist at Christie 's auction house provided to CNN|prep\ta statement Peter Klarnet , lead book and manuscript specialist at Christie 's auction house provided to CNN|pobj\tPeter|compound\tPeter Klarnet , lead book and manuscript specialist at Christie 's auction house|nsubj\tlead|amod\tbook and manuscript|nmod\tlead book and manuscript specialist at Christie 's auction house|appos\tPeter Klarnet , lead book and manuscript specialist at Christie 's auction house provided to CNN|relcl"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "The letter, written in German one year before one of the most important minds in history death and transcribed in English by Christie's auction house , is a reaction to the 1952 Religious Philosopher Erik Gutkind book, Choose Life: The Biblical Call of Revolt.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "Who transcribed the letter?",
                    "answer": "Christie's auction house"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What book was written in German one year before Adolf Hitler's death?",
                    "score": 0.8041,
                    "answers": "the 1952 Religious Philosopher Erik Gutkind book , Choose Life : The Biblical Call of Revolt|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What year was the letter written in German?",
                    "score": 0.7686,
                    "answers": "one year before one of the most important minds in history death|prep"
                },
                {
                    "question": "Who wrote the book, Choose Life: The Biblical Call of Revolt?",
                    "score": 0.6714,
                    "answers": "Religious|amod"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What was the name of the book that was transcribed in German?",
                    "score": 0.593,
                    "answers": "that The letter , written in German one year before one of the most important minds in history death and transcribed in English by Christie 's auction house , is a reaction to the 1952 Religious Philosopher Erik Gutkind book , Choose Life : The Biblical Call of Revolt|ccomp"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "While one of the most important minds in history makes it clear that one of the most important minds in history and Religious Philosopher Erik Gutkind have much in common with regard to the objective attitude of human life and community, one of the most important minds in history clearly and abundantly leaves position on religion.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "Who reported on 04/12/2018 that one of the most important minds in history makes clear that one of the most important minds in history and Religious Philosopher Erik Gutkind have much in common with regard to the objective attitude of human life and community?",
                    "answer": "cnnespanol.cnn.com"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What is Erika Gutkind's position on religion?",
                    "score": 0.6852,
                    "answers": "cnnespanol.cnn.com reported on 04/12/2018 that While one of the most important minds in history makes it clear that one of the most important minds in history and Religious Philosopher Erik Gutkind have much in common with regard to the objective attitude of human life and community , one of the most important minds in history clearly and abundantly leaves position on religion|ROOT\tthat|mark\tWhile|mark\tthe|det\tmost|advmod\tin history|prep\thistory|pobj\tit|nsubj\tthat|mark\tthe|det\tmost|advmod\tin history|prep\thistory|pobj\tReligious Philosopher|compound\tErik|compound\tthe|det\t,|punct\tthe|det\tmost|advmod\tin history|prep\thistory|pobj\tclearly and abundantly|advmod\tabundantly|conj\ton religion|prep\treligion|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the position on religion?",
                    "score": 0.6534,
                    "answers": "position on religion|dobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What are the objectives of human life and community?",
                    "score": 0.6347,
                    "answers": "most important|amod\tmost important|amod\tin common|prep\tcommon|pobj\thuman life and community|pobj\tmost important|amod"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "The word God is nothing more than for one of the most important minds in history the expression and product of human weakness, the Bible is a collection of honorable legends, but still purely primitive, which however are quite childish, writes one of the most important minds in history .",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "Who reported on 04/12/2018 that The word God is nothing more than for one of the most important minds in history the expression and product of human weakness?",
                    "answer": "cnnespanol.cnn.com"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "Who wrote the Bible?",
                    "score": 0.7207,
                    "answers": "of the most important minds in history|prep\tthe most important minds in history|pobj\tone of the most important minds in history|nsubj\tof the most important minds in history|prep\tthe most important minds in history|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the meaning of the word God?",
                    "score": 0.6119,
                    "answers": "cnnespanol.cnn.com reported on 04/12/2018|ccomp\tThe|det\tThe word God|nsubj\tGod|appos\tThe word God is nothing more than for one of the most important minds in history the expression and product of human weakness|ccomp\tnothing more than for one of the most important minds in history the expression and product of human weakness|attr\tmore|amod\tthan for one of the most important minds in history the expression and product of human weakness|prep\tfor one of the most important minds in history the expression and product of human weakness|pobj\tone of the most important minds in history the expression and product of human weakness|pobj\tmost|advmod\tthe expression and product of human weakness|appos\tproduct|conj\thuman|amod\tThe word God is nothing more than for one of the most important minds in history the expression and product of human weakness , the Bible is a collection of honorable legends , but still purely primitive , which however are quite childish|ccomp\twhich however are quite childish|relcl\tcnnespanol.cnn.com reported on 04/12/2018 that The word God is nothing more than for one of the most important minds in history the expression and product of human weakness , the Bible is a collection of honorable legends , but still purely primitive , which however are quite childish , writes one of the most important minds in history|ROOT\tmost|advmod"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is human weakness?",
                    "score": 0.5749,
                    "answers": "of human weakness|prep\thuman weakness|pobj"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "one of the most important minds in history was a German-born Jew who lost religious faith at an early age and sometimes referred to one of the most important minds in history as an agnostic.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "What happened to one of the most important minds in history?",
                    "answer": "lost religious faith at an early age"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "When did one of the most important minds lose religious faith at an early age?",
                    "score": 0.82,
                    "answers": "at an early age|prep"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is an agnostic?",
                    "score": 0.6334,
                    "answers": "sometimes referred to one of the most important minds in history as an agnostic|conj\tas an agnostic|prep\tan agnostic|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is cnnespanol.cnn.com?",
                    "score": 0.5468,
                    "answers": "the|det\thistory|pobj\t-|punct\tand|cc\tthe|det\thistory|pobj"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "The letter reinforces his love and shared identity with the Jewish people, but it also calls Judaism, like all other religions  an incarnation of the most childish superstition.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "Who reported that the letter reinforced his love and shared identity with the Jewish people?",
                    "answer": "cnnespanol.cnn.com"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What religions does the letter link to?",
                    "score": 0.8596,
                    "answers": "other|amod"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What does cnnespanol.cnn.com call Judaism?",
                    "score": 0.8492,
                    "answers": "on 04/12/2018|prep\tit also calls Judaism , like all other religions|conj\t  an incarnation of the most childish superstition|dep\tan incarnation of the most childish superstition|attr\tof the most childish superstition|prep\tmost childish|amod\tthe most childish superstition|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What does the letter say about Jewish people?",
                    "score": 0.8365,
                    "answers": "cnnespanol.cnn.com reported on 04/12/2018 that The letter reinforces his love and shared identity with the Jewish people , but it also calls Judaism , like all other religions|ROOT"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What does cnnespanol.cnn.com say about the letter?",
                    "score": 0.7299,
                    "answers": "that|mark\tThe|det\tThe letter|nsubj\tand|cc\tshared identity|conj\tthe|det\t,|punct\tbut|cc\tit|nsubj\talso|advmod\t,|punct\tlike all other religions|prep\tall|det\tan|det\tthe|det\tmost|advmod"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "The letter, which was sold on eBay in 2012, was exhibited at the Pace Gallery in San Francisco in late November until its auction in New York.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "Where was The letter exhibited until it was auctioned in New York?",
                    "answer": "Pace Gallery"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What was the name of the letter sold on eBay in 2012?",
                    "score": 0.6302,
                    "answers": "in late November|prep\tlate|amod\tuntil its auction in New York|prep\tits auction in New York|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "Where is the Pace Gallery in San Francisco located?",
                    "score": 0.5932,
                    "answers": "at the Pace Gallery in San Francisco|prep\tthe Pace Gallery in San Francisco|pobj"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "It is not Einstein's only missive that has attracted great interest in Christie's.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "Who reported on 04/12/2018 that It is not Einstein's only missive that attracted great interest in Christie's?",
                    "answer": "cnnespanol.cnn.com"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What does cnnespanol.cnn.com say about Eton's missive?",
                    "score": 0.8505,
                    "answers": "that|mark\tIt|nsubj\t's|case\tthat|nsubj\thas|aux\t's|case"
                },
                {
                    "question": "Who is interested in Christie's missive?",
                    "score": 0.8481,
                    "answers": "that has attracted great interest in Christie 's|ccomp"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the interest in Christie's missive?",
                    "score": 0.8076,
                    "answers": "great interest in Christie 's|dobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the relationship between Eton with Christie's missive?",
                    "score": 0.7875,
                    "answers": "in Christie 's|prep"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the source of evidence of Eberman's missive?",
                    "score": 0.7651,
                    "answers": "Einstein 's only missive|attr"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "In 2002, the auction house exhibited a 1939 written letter from Einstein to the then President of the United States, Franklin Delano Roosevelt.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "Who was the President of the United States in 1939?",
                    "answer": "Franklin Delano Roosevelt"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What type of letter did Franklin Delano Roosevelt write?",
                    "score": 0.7981,
                    "answers": "written|amod"
                },
                {
                    "question": "Who wrote the letter from Einstein to the President of the United States?",
                    "score": 0.7154,
                    "answers": "Franklin|compound"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What did the auction house exhibit in 2002 about Franklin Delano Roosevelt?",
                    "score": 0.69,
                    "answers": "cnnespanol.cnn.com reported on 04/12/2018 that In 2002 , the auction house exhibited a 1939 written letter from Einstein to the then President of the United States , Franklin Delano Roosevelt|ROOT\tthat In 2002 , the auction house exhibited a 1939 written letter from Einstein to the then President of the United States , Franklin Delano Roosevelt|ccomp"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is the name of the letter from Franklin Delano Roosevelt to President Roosevelt?",
                    "score": 0.5791,
                    "answers": "on 04/12/2018|prep\tIn 2002|prep\tof the United States|prep"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What is cnnespanol.cnn.com?",
                    "score": 0.5209,
                    "answers": "that|mark\t,|punct\tthe|det\tauction|compound\ta|det\tthe|det\tthen|advmod\tthe|det\tUnited|compound\t,|punct"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "claim": "The letter warned Roosevelt of the dangers of nuclear bomb technology.",
            "question_answers": [
                {
                    "question": "What website reported on the dangers of nuclear bomb technology?",
                    "answer": "cnnespanol.cnn.com"
                }
            ],
            "focal_questions": [
                {
                    "question": "What did the letter warned Roosevelt about the dangers of nuclear bomb technology?",
                    "score": 0.8856,
                    "answers": "cnnespanol.cnn.com reported on 04/12/2018 that The letter warned Roosevelt of the dangers of nuclear bomb technology|ROOT\ton 04/12/2018|prep\tthat|mark\tThe|det\tthat The letter warned Roosevelt of the dangers of nuclear bomb technology|ccomp\tof the dangers of nuclear bomb technology|prep\tthe|det\tthe dangers of nuclear bomb technology|pobj\tnuclear|amod\tnuclear bomb|compound\tnuclear bomb technology|pobj"
                },
                {
                    "question": "What does cnnespanol.cnn.com say about nuclear bomb technology?",
                    "score": 0.8459,
                    "answers": "of nuclear bomb technology|prep"
                }
            ]
        }
    ]
}